You are listening [music] to Golden Rule
Radio, your weekly discussion of the
precious metals markets and the markets
closely associated with the metals. I'm
Tory alongside Miles and Rob and
together we have over 80 years of
experience advising on and brokering the
precious metals and each week the three
of us like to provide a technical
analysis of the metals charts and then
cover the underlying fundamentals and
the news that helps move and predict
those markets and make those charts go
where Miles says they're going to go.
>> Cuz he's the chart monkey.
>> That's right. That's Miles' job. So we
always start with Miles on a weekly
recap. Show us the charts for the week
and for those of you who are interested
in seeing the visuals you can find them
on our website which is
mackalvany.com/radio.
>> Thanks Tory. I got to find where I've
got that little bit map chart monkey
character on my computer.
>> Dot plot? Do you have your own dot plot?
>> I don't know what a dot plot is.
>> Well, the Fed doesn't anymore either but
we'll get to that later in the show.
>> [laughter]
>> So I was thinking about an old dot
matrix printer that my dad had back in
the 80s but that's a different thing.
>> I know what one of those are.
>> you had a couple. So what goes down must
come up. You know, last week's opening
charts was a pretty consistent
everything's down week. This week we've
got the opposite with everything up
although not up quite as much as it
would have been if we had recorded our
show a couple hours ago. So we will
>> [laughter]
>> we will talk about the FOMC here in a
little bit as we have a new Fed chair
kicking off his maiden voyage
this Wednesday here. So
starting off with gold up about four and
a quarter. So 4.25%
up hitting us at 4,250.
I did not make that up. Those are the
same numbers and it just happened to
work out that way. Now, gold was up as
much as about 7 and 1/2% prior to the
FOMC and that's going to be a running
theme as we go through the charts this
week. So, the FOMC did have a buy the
rumor, sell the news event as we always
expect. But, even still, gold up almost
4 and 1/2% just since our recording last
week. Silver, not to be outdone, as
always, anything gold does silver does
better, up 5 and 1/2% currently sitting
at 6750.
So, 5 and 1/2% up to $67.50
as silver was coming off a pretty solid
low
>> [laughter]
>> here a couple days ago. But, silver guys
was up as much as 12 and 1/2% this week
prior to the FOMC. So, silver continues
to be incredibly volatile on a
week-to-week basis and we're not even at
$100 silver. You know, this is after the
correction. We're still seeing 10, 12
plus percent weeks up and down. Moving
over to the other white metals, platinum
up 7 and 1/2% currently sitting at
1,730.
Same story, higher a few hours ago.
Palladium, same story, up about 5 and
1/2% since our recording last week,
sitting just under 1,300. So, platinum
continues to beat palladium. The S&P up
1.8% to 7,420.
Same story, the S&P was up almost 4% at
one point this past week. But,
interestingly, the S&P started to slip
prior, a couple days prior to the FOMC
today. And that high it put in earlier
this week was not as strong as what we
saw back on June 2nd. So, we're
certainly hoping the S&P is stair
stepping its way back up, but we'll have
to see how it does depending on what the
interest rates are doing and any money
that may be getting pumped into that
market. And finally, the dollar is also
up. Everything's up this week. The
dollar's up half a percent. Now, the
difference here is the dollar was
actually on a downward slide all week,
so it was sell the rumor, buy the news
in terms of the US dollar. It was on a
downward slide all week until post FOMC
today where the dollar jumped up just
under 1%. It was about
.83, .85%
today. So, prior to the FOMC, the dollar
was down on the week, but we did have a
nice little bump up here on new interest
rate moves. So, moving over to what
happened here at the FOMC, I'm going to
let somebody else talk.
>> Well, a lot did happen and it's not just
cuz Orsh had his first press conference
and first meeting, but the whole world
has been kind of waiting and watching.
Japan had a rate increase, which is a
completely different discussion.
I kind of thought the Federal Reserve
might do a quarter point hike here now
because of that.
>> Surprised and it was unanimous.
>> The vote was unanimous, yeah. The
expectations are not. I mean, the
expectations nine of the 18 who voted on
the dot plot, right? Which is each
member basically gets up in front of the
classroom and puts a dot on where they
think interest rates are going to be in
the future. So, they do 2026, 2027,
2028, and then longer term. And the
update is good because people kind of
see, well, what does the Federal Reserve
think interest rates are going to do?
And
nine of the 18 felt like there needed to
be a rate hike in 2026. Nine of the 18
felt like they could remain unchanged or
even be lowered. So, there is some
division in terms of the forecast, but
in terms of today's vote, yeah, you're
right, Rob, it's unanimous.
We'll see what transpires from that.
I'll tell you
what we did learn is that the dot plot,
it sounds like it's going to go away.
So, Warsh is not a big fan of the
forecasting.
So, it's called forward guidance. And
so, the markets are going to have
less of the Fed's opinion on what things
look like going forward. And predicting
the economy's impossible anyway. You
know, everybody would be billionaires if
if you could actually do it, but he did
establish five new independent task
forces to oversee five key areas, but
most importantly, they left the rates
unchanged at 3.5 to 3.75%,
and again, at least half feel like it's
going to remain there really through
2027, according to the dot plot. So,
don't look for interest rates to really
be coming down, you know, over the next
year and a half. They don't feel like
PCE is going to return to its 2% target
until deep into 2028.
>> When you say PCE, you're referring to
price earnings ratio?
>> No, the PCE is the personal consumption
expenditures, and that's released each
month also, but that's basically the
cost of living. You know, what are we
spending, in a sense, and that's what
one of their objectives is is to keep
inflation in check, which means keeping
prices of all goods sold in check.
>> Yeah, well, the big driver behind
consumer prices is the cost of oil, and
that has come down. We'll see what
happens this weekend in Switzerland
during their
signing of the memorandum of
understanding, which has another 2
months to hammer out details.
Not much to really criticize about. I
mean, it's not what we had hoped for.
It's a little bit like kissing your
sister through the screen door.
But in the meantime, our market is going
to be driven a lot by what happens this
weekend. I mean, we're not even taking
trades without funds in house going into
this weekend cuz either it's going to be
great news and the market's going to
start moving back up. When I say market,
gold and silver,
or it's going to be another one of those
rug pulled out from underneath the peace
process and the metals are going to
crater. I doubt seriously if we're at
the same price level this time next week
as we are today.
>> Well, I had a conversation with somebody
outside of the office. It wasn't another
broker at Macleavy and Precious Metals,
but I was saying the same thing about
this week because you had
that MOU kind of being developed and
they were talking about it, but you had
Warsh's first Fed announcement, right?
This first FOMC.
And it's not like you can predict up or
down, but we knew there'd be some
volatility. And I think you're totally
right, Rob, that that's going to
continue for another week that we don't
know. And And look at the reversal in
gold. I mean, that's 3% down, silver
down more than 4%, the ratio back up
another point to above 62.
And that's another huge swing. And why
is that happening? It's happening
because Treasury yield spiked after the
Fed announcement. Okay, it's strong
dollar policy. Interest rates are going
to remain higher. So, the Treasury
market cast its vote on the dot plot,
too,
and said that the rates are going up.
And then certainly the US dollar rally
that Miles started with is big. So, gold
goes down that way. But if they actually
do some strong dollar policy, it's okay
for gold to come down. Remember, it
reacts more than it predicts.
>> Well, that's true.
>> So, we're not in the job of predicting
gold price, either. We just want to tell
it like it is, tell you why it's
reacting the way it is.
And it is important to know that markets
move when people say things. And whether
it's monetary policy, like the Fed has,
or it's fiscal policy, like the Treasury
has, the US government spending,
it matters. And the Dow Jones Industrial
Average, last I looked, was down like
800 points after the announcement. The
S&P erased like 1.2 trillion dollars in
under two hours.
>> Yeah.
>> All since that Fed announcement about
two and a half hours ago.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we'll see if if those markets remain
volatile as well. It's not just the
metals.
>> Yeah. There's a lot going on.
>> Yeah. Yeah, and my understanding of the
MOU, the memorandum of understanding is
that there's not a whole lot that's
really understood.
>> [laughter]
>> So,
we'll see.
>> Well, you mentioned those Treasury
yields and like you pull up something
like say, you know, a reasonable time
like the yield on the five-year which is
currently sitting at uh about 4 and 1/4%
with US interest rates down at what
3.75.
Last time yields were here, US interest
rates, this would have go back to
February of last year, interest rates
were at around 4 and 1/2. So, we're
looking at yields starting to rise even
though interest rates haven't. And I'm
wondering if that is a concern for
rising yields, higher return. I mean,
there's maybe market concerns, there's
potential instability like Rob was
saying, there's concern over what's
going on with Iran and potential
hopefully
uh some peace deals brokered this coming
weekend. But there's definitely a flight
from riskier assets, you know, risk-off
assets into more consistent or more
guaranteed returns even in the liquidity
side of things as those yields are
starting to push up quite a bit, bit
more than we've seen in a long time,
above where the interest rates
themselves actually are.
>> But I also think it's a factor. I mean,
typically if you have a flight to
safety, yields will come down as people
load into Treasuries.
And I think you're having more
Treasuries being laid off into the
market than there are people standing
ready to buy.
So, I think the flight to safety doesn't
appear to be the US Treasuries, but
where is it going?
>> Yeah, where is it going? I mean, 45% of
central banks, you guys the World Gold
Council just released this.
>> Saw that.
>> Said they plan to buy gold over the next
12 months. That's the highest reading on
record. So, again, if the biggest money
is doing it, why aren't we doing it? And
I talked to somebody yesterday who came
in to a massive exit. It's kind of like
the SpaceX story that you hear about.
Yeah. You know, these people become
overnight millionaires.
And explaining the role of gold and the
conservative approach, the hedge and the
asset preservation that it is.
You take a certain portion of your
investment portfolio, you sock it away.
And if you look at the investment
triangle that we go through, which we're
happy to talk with you about and it's
been decades since we've recommended and
it works over time.
>> Yeah.
>> None of this stuff really matters. It's
all noise. If you allocate your assets
in such a way that you're diversified
truly, not just in stocks and bonds.
Right? But you do have metals and you
have a cash position and you're getting
some yield and return and you've got
some other growth and income options.
I'm telling you, it just works, but at
the end of the conversation, it was
still
kind of like, "Well, you know, how much
do you put into gold? One 1%?
>> Mhm.
>> 2%?" And it's like, they're missing it.
>> The market hasn't given them any reason,
you know, people have a fear of missing
out. And if they see the market running
higher, that gives them more desire to
be in it. When the market is like where
we are now, I mean, Miles show that
chart. I mean, we've hit
in the 38 to 4100 dollar price range
three times in the last what?
>> Year?
>> Yeah.
>> This is a great time to be stepping in.
I mean, you look at the charts and you
go, "That's what I want to buy. I want
to buy where I know where the floor is
and I'm not going to get burned, and
we're within 2 and 1/2, 3% of what we
believe is
very likely the floor of the price, but
it's not giving them any There's no
excitement. You know, I want to buy
SpaceX when it's going up.
>> up 20% a day after the IPO, after the
launch.
>> That's exciting.
>> Not rocket launch, but the IPO launch.
>> Yeah, it's That's exciting. That's what
I want to I want to be in that.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, sometimes it just doesn't. For the
same reason why people who understand
the precious metals market, as you guys
probably are also finding out right now,
are buying a lot of precious metals
right now.
You know, we've got There is a
significant amount of precious metals
going out the door right now. I would
argue, at least for a company like ours,
more going out the door for us right now
than there was back in January,
February. Now, January, February was a
little bit different because again, most
of our clients who understand the
triangle concept and are building
towards pieces of the same puzzle, we're
looking at things like ratio trading
between gold or silver or rebalancing
between their metals and their stock
portfolio. You know, so there was There
was a transfer of assets between kind of
predecided, preorganized buckets that we
put our investments into. But what I'm
getting right now is just phone calls.
Hey, silver's off by half. I enjoyed
that run. Are things quiet? It's June.
I'm going to pick up some more right
now. And
>> It's not quiet.
>> yeah, it's not quiet. Well, and you
mentioned a minute ago, it's like, well,
where is this rush to liquidity? I mean,
obviously we're seeing some of it in the
US dollar with the yields pushing a
decent clip above [snorts]
the US interest rates, which
historically only happens in a period of
time where generally people are
expecting interest rates to be rising.
Is when you look at the interest rate
chart overlaid with the yield chart, you
tend to see periods where the interest
rates rising and the yields tend to
exceed that kind of in anticipation.
But you brought up the point of you
said, "Where's the rush to liquidity
internationally if it's not going into
Treasury bills?" Well, we already know
the answer to that. Gold's up 40% and
silver's doubled in the last year.
We know where the rush to liquidity is
going. It's been obvious for years. It's
going into the best performing asset of
the last 20 years.
>> Not necessarily in the United States,
but most certainly in Asia. And I'm
grateful for our clientele because they
do get it and we are busy and money is
coming in and it's exciting.
>> Yeah. Well, to that point, 20% of
central bank asset holdings are now
gold. It's exceeding 20%. It's 1.4%
of the individual retail investor in the
United States. That's a big disparity
and it goes right back to my
conversation where they're missing the
mark. And what percentage of your
portfolio, according to Morgan Stanley
CIO last year? 20%. So, time to step up
and buy the dips.
>> Yep. Yeah. Yeah, you increase your
metals position when nobody else wants
it.
And then you reorganize your metals
position when everybody else wants it.
Because that's where the opportunities
come in and and I think we've worked
very hard for a long time to try to
teach people that. So, it's kind of fun
seeing the fruits of the effort. And
speaking to my personal clients out
there that do listen to the show
occasionally, just appreciate working
with you guys and keeping a cool head in
January and February.
>> Yep, and I feel the same way and I'd
like to end on that note and just really
tell our clients how much we appreciate
them. We really appreciate them
listening cuz there's a lot of different
podcasts that people can be listening to
and they choose to listen to ours and we
are grateful.
>> Here, here. Well, that's going to do it
this week for Golden Rule Radio. As
always, we appreciate you stopping by.
If you liked what you heard, we
encourage you to head on over to our
website, where you can find additional
information for your precious metals
portfolio. We are at mcalvany.com.
That's m c a l v a n y dot com. You can
also find us on Twitter at ICA Gold or
Facebook at McAlvany Financial. And as
always, if you'd like to discuss your
personal portfolio, especially that
triangle, with one of the advisors here
at McAlvany Precious Metals, you can
reach us at 1-800-525-9556.
Thanks for listening.
Have a great week.